Guide to the Collection on the Cuban Slave Trade MSS.569
Fales Library and Special Collections
Collection on the Cuban Slave Trade
1809-1898
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fales Library
MSS.569
.5 linear foot in 2 flat boxes
This collection consists of documents concerning slavery in Cuba between 1809 and 1898. Materials include telegrams, contracts, identification papers, travel licenses, marriage and baptism records, death and burial certificates, purchase and insurance documents, and manumission records documenting various aspects of slavery in Cuba, including the economics of the Atlantic slave trade, demographics of Cuban populations, England's abolition of slavery, the transportation of Chinese workers to Cuba, family relationships in the context of slavery, living and working conditions on sugar cane plantations, and manumission processes.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of documents concerning slavery in Cuba between 1809 and 1898. Materials include telegrams, contracts, identification papers, travel licenses, marriage and baptism records, death and burial certificates, purchase and insurance documents, and manumission records documenting various aspects of slavery in Cuba, including the economics of the Atlantic slave trade, demographics of Cuban populations, England's abolition of slavery, the transportation of Chinese workers to Cuba, family relationships in the context of slavery, living and working conditions on sugar cane plantations, and manumission processes.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection were purchased from a bookseller in 2017; original provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this purchase is 2019.010.
Separated Materials
Folder 1 in the inventory, a grouping of 80 documents concerning a case of five slaves at a sugar mill who killed a man they believed to be the Governor General of Cuba, was removed from the collection and cataloged separately as HV6535.C9 C66 1842.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the seller.
Slave trade -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Economic aspects -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Social aspects -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Foreign workers, Chinese -- Cuba.; Chinese -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Vital statistics records; Free papers
- Cuban manuscript concerning the deposit of black cimarrones in prison, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cuban telegram on the persecution of trafficking and slavery, sent to Lieutenant Governor General Cardenas., August 1857 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cuban death certificate for a Chinese slave. It certifies that 'Estanislao, and Asiatic man' died at Charity Hospital of San Felipe y Santiago, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- La Protectora insurance policy on the life of a slave, showing the value of the premium and other details. From 'Comapnia General Cubana de Seguros Mutuos Sobre La Vida de Esclavos', 1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Certificate of burial for the newborn baby of a slave issued by the Church of the Holy Spirit in Havana. Another document issued by the Church of Monserrate for the same person, August 7, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Document providing details summarizing slave expenditures, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- La Providencia insurance on a slave, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Document of a marriage between slaves, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Sobre Desobediencia Negro Cargador de Cadaveres, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Identity paper for a female slave named 'Dominga', 1856 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Identity paper for a slave named Geronimo Ganga, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Document granting freedom to a slave named Lelicia Frenyo, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Document relating to payment for the burial of a slave, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Document of the baptism of a Moreno named Francisco Herera, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Freedom papers for a slave named Rosa Delgado, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- La Protectora insurance for a slave, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Telegram concerning the persecution of the slave trade by the Lieutenant Governor of Cuba, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Document Deposito Judicial de Esclavos, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- La Protectora slave insurance document, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Stamped document for renting out a slave, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Document for the deposit of a slave, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- La Providencia insurance for a slave, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Identification paper for a slave named Guillermo, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Report of the landing of "muzzle", 1864 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Document of marriage between two slaves belonging to a cavalry officer, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Telegram on the persecution of the slave trade from Captain Pral, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Document of a marriage between two slaves, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- La Providencia insurance for a slave, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Document of marriage between a free Cuban slave and a free Venezuelan slave, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Telegram relating to the slave trade, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Group of five documents concerning the drowning of a slave in a well and details of the investigation and his burial, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Two manuscripts documenting the death of a creole Moreno slave named Juan Delgado who drowned in a well, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Document on the departure of a slave, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Unidentified slave document, stamped, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Chinese worker identification issued at 'Gobierno Politico de la Habana'. Left and right margins contain 9 articles which quote laws and regulations pertaining to 'cedulas' and the mid section contains information on the Chinese worker named Anselmo., 1863 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Contract for a Spanish slave from Palma in the Balearic Islands, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Chinese slave contract from Guanajay and signed by a 28 year old from Canton, June 1868 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Chinese slave contract from Guanajay and signed by a 28 year old from Canton, May 1868 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Document of the death and burial of a Chinese worker, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Chinese slave contract issued at the "Gobierno Politico de la Habana" and signed by a 28 year old, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Chinese Slave identification "Cedula" Document issued at the "Gobierno Politico de la Habana", 1863 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Contract for a group of nine Spanish Slaves who were bounded and owned by this contract to one Saypa Hernandez. The third page contains a list of nine slaves included in this contract and five columns of data relating to each slave, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Document issued by Captain General of Cuba Geronimo Valdes. It is a memorandum which informs of an illegal disembarkation of escaped slaves who later hid in a farm near Matanzas. Curiously Valdes states that this information was passed by the British., 1842 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Biographical Note
  Jerónimo Valdés (1784–1855) was a Spanish military figure and administrator. Born in Villarín, in Asturias, he participated in the battle of Ayacucho (1824), which was a defeat for the Spanish. He served as Viceroy of Navarre from 1833 to 1834 and also served as Minister of War. He fought on the Liberal (Isabeline) side in the First Carlist War. Valdés lost the Battle of Artaza (April 22, 1835). Valdés signed the Lord Eliot Convention soon after, regulating the treatment of prisoners during that war. He later served as captain-general of Valencia, and of Galicia, and served as governor of Cuba from 1841 to September 1843.
- Set of three documents written in Havana, Cuba dated February 1856 and totalling 8 pages. They deal with the sale of Sugar Mill 'La Constancia' including the slaves who worked at it. The file includes a 2 page list with 72 slaves to be included in the sale (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Formal declaration by a priest/cura of a newly-baptised slave claiming freedom, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Contract for a 28 year old Chinese slave from Canton, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Cuban license for four Congo slaves to travel freely by train. It is signed by Governor Leopoldo O'Donnell, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Cuban license for 36 slaves to travel freely by train to work on a sugar plantation. Each slave is mentioned by name. It is signed by Governor Leopoldo O'Donnell, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Document written in Aranjuez, Spain. It was written at the Presidencia del Consejo de Ministerio de Ultramar and addressed to the Captain General of Cuba Domingo Dulce y Garay, who signed it upon receipt in Havana. The document discusses a fine of 30 pesos for owners of escaped slaves, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Labor contract issued in Cuba for a Spanish laborer, a colono slave originally from Tenerife in the Canary Islands, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Contract for group of 28 Spanish slaves, including the list of slaves. Written in Havana it is 3 pages of text. They were bonded and owned by this contract to one Saypa Hernandez, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Puerto Rican slave registry document, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Manuscript news bulletin on emancipated slave who was subsequently robbed, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Manuscript of a baptismal declaration for two slaves (one from the Congo (aged 19) and the other (aged 12) from Macua (Macao?)). The slaves belong to a sub-lieutenant in the militia, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Birth declaration. The mother is a 'free brown' woman, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Slave declaration attesting to having a slave grandfather, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Declaration of a baby born to two slaves, one from Congo and the other from Ganga, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Request to have a newborn slave baptized. The mother is a slave and the father is unknown, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Statement of baptism of a black Congo slave who belongs to the 'Commission of the Railroad', 1836 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Manuscript discussing captured slaves, one from the Congo, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Declaration that the Sacred Sacrement is being given to a black native slave, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Declaration of the birth of a child to a slave mother, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Manuscript giving a name to a newly born slave child, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Undated (1860s) statement that the God-Mother of the 'freed slaves' is Martina Abasi, of the nation 'Carabali' (Box 2, Folder 65)
- Undated declaration of the birth of a baby of 'All Saints' who has 'free brown people' for godparents, 1850s (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Birth declaration of a baby born to a 'free brown' woman, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 67)
- Manuscript discussing the Sacred Sacrament of Baptism being given to a baby, daughter of a native slave, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 68)
- Havana birth declaration followed with a statement saying an emancipated Congo slave is in the care of a Colonel and has a slave Godfather, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Manuscript news bulletin discussing a fight between two slaves from different owners, one sustaining a lesion, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 70)
- Birth declaration (Godmother is a slave), 1877 (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Undated manuscript concerning two slaves that are listed but not appearing on a ships list (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Declaration of the birth of a baby to two slave parents, one from the Congo and the other from Ganga, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 73)
- Four page manuscript concerning a fugitive from a train that is an emancipated Congo slave, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 74)
- Manuscript showing a chart on the emancipation of five slaves, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Manumission document granting freedom to a slave boy who is less than a year old, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 76)
- Death certificate for a Chinese man named Domingo at the Hospital de Caridad de San Felipe y Santiago, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 77)
- Chart with details of five newly emancipated slaves (split down fold), 1881 (Box 2, Folder 78)
- Manuscript concerning an fugitive emancipated slave that was found in a Havana 'deposito', 1868 (Box 2, Folder 79)
- Manuscript statement of the birth of a baby born to 'all slaves', 1851 (Box 2, Folder 80)
- Birth declaration for a 'brown woman', 1898 (Box 2, Folder 81)
- Birth declaration (likely slaves), 1838 (Box 2, Folder 82)
- Manuscript stating that a 'legitimate' child was born, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 83)
- Manuscript of a birth declaration (likely slave), 1848 (Box 2, Folder 84)
- Ganga (Africa) off of ship 'Goleta', 1844 (Box 2, Folder 85)
- Manuscript of priest presenting two criados for service, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 86)